<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Behavioral Ethics Lab</title>
    <link>https://www.behavioralethics.org/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.behavioralethics.org/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Behavioral Ethics Lab © 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.behavioralethics.org/media/icon_hue79c9617451b43386f4505d9bbf948d0_14414_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://www.behavioralethics.org/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trustpath</title>
      <link>https://www.behavioralethics.org/project/trustpath/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behavioralethics.org/project/trustpath/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3&gt; The importance of trust in the sharing economy &lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;The collaborative economy covers a variety of sectors and is rapidly emerging across Europe. Adding hundreds of billions of euro to the EU economy, it offers more choices to consumers and new opportunities to entrepreneurs. However, little is known about the bottom-up psychological factors driving the collaborative economy users’ behaviour. For responsible sharing, trust is necessary but not sufficient. The EU-funded TRUSTPATH project will develop and test a psychological theory of how people use the collaborative economy. The hypothesis is that trust encouraged without transparency can lead users to neglect the negative side effects trade has on others. The findings will advance our understanding of the psychology of the collaborative economy and inform policymakers seeking to regulate it. The results will also be useful for companies seeking to promote responsible sharing among users.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-this-project-has-received-funding-from-the-european-research-council-erc-under-the-european-unions-horizon-2020-research-and-innovation-programme-grant-agreement-no-865931&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;This project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union&amp;#39;s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (Grant agreement No. 865931).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/trustpath/eu-logo-bw_hud89cc0504c815f82b12534a9ae8558d8_100613_9427ca6963392d992712c474c93f5a8e.jpg 400w,
               /project/trustpath/eu-logo-bw_hud89cc0504c815f82b12534a9ae8558d8_100613_3265f8091cf9b924f82cbfedc7c65e12.jpg 760w,
               /project/trustpath/eu-logo-bw_hud89cc0504c815f82b12534a9ae8558d8_100613_1200x1200_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://www.behavioralethics.org/project/trustpath/eu-logo-bw_hud89cc0504c815f82b12534a9ae8558d8_100613_9427ca6963392d992712c474c93f5a8e.jpg&#34;
               width=&#34;200px&#34;
               height=&#34;322&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      This project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union&amp;rsquo;s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (Grant agreement No. 865931).
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-this-project-is-financially-supported-by-the-dutch-research-council-nwo-with-project-number-195137&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;This project is financially supported by the Dutch Research Council (NWO) with project number 195.137.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/trustpath/nwo-logo-bw_huaa0fcde34bac153e467298c2ba83850c_6664_08a74485892ea62e7254973d7a94601b.png 400w,
               /project/trustpath/nwo-logo-bw_huaa0fcde34bac153e467298c2ba83850c_6664_eec78651c62bf7cd32ad3b85fa9ccdac.png 760w,
               /project/trustpath/nwo-logo-bw_huaa0fcde34bac153e467298c2ba83850c_6664_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_2.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://www.behavioralethics.org/project/trustpath/nwo-logo-bw_huaa0fcde34bac153e467298c2ba83850c_6664_08a74485892ea62e7254973d7a94601b.png&#34;
               width=&#34;200px&#34;
               height=&#34;230&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      This project is financially supported by the Dutch Research Council (NWO) with project number 195.137.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Corruption</title>
      <link>https://www.behavioralethics.org/project/roots_of_corruption/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behavioralethics.org/project/roots_of_corruption/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3&gt; At the roots of corruption: a behavioral ethics approach &lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;For many years, human cooperation has been praised as beneficial in organizational and personal settings. Indeed, cooperation allows people to develop trust, build meaningful relationships, achieve mutually beneficial outcomes, and strengthen bonding with one&amp;rsquo;s group members. However, while the benefits of cooperation are clear, very little is known about its possible negative aspects. Such negative aspects include the potential emergence of unethical conduct among cooperating partners, or as termed here – corrupt collaboration. Such joint unethical efforts, benefiting (directly or indirectly) one or more of the involved parties, occur in business, sports, and even academia. Corrupt collaboration emerges when one party bends ethical rules (here: lie) to set the stage for another party to further bend ethical rules and get the job done, that is, secure personal profit based on joint unethical acts. We propose that corrupt collaborations most commonly occur when all involved parties gain from the corrupt behavior. The current proposal is aimed at unfolding the roots and nature of corrupt collaborations; their existence, the psychological and biological processes underlying them, and the settings most likely to make corrupt collaboration emerge and spread. Accordingly, the information gathered in the current proposal has the potential to change the commonly held conceptions regarding the unidimensional – positive – nature of cooperation. It will help create a comprehensive understanding of cooperation and, specifically, when it should be encouraged or, alternatively, monitored.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-this-project-has-received-funding-from-the-european-research-council-erc-under-the-european-unions-horizon-2020-research-and-innovation-programme-grant-agreement-no-637915&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;This project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union&amp;#39;s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (Grant agreement No. 637915).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/roots_of_corruption/eu-logo-bw_hud89cc0504c815f82b12534a9ae8558d8_100613_9427ca6963392d992712c474c93f5a8e.jpg 400w,
               /project/roots_of_corruption/eu-logo-bw_hud89cc0504c815f82b12534a9ae8558d8_100613_3265f8091cf9b924f82cbfedc7c65e12.jpg 760w,
               /project/roots_of_corruption/eu-logo-bw_hud89cc0504c815f82b12534a9ae8558d8_100613_1200x1200_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://www.behavioralethics.org/project/roots_of_corruption/eu-logo-bw_hud89cc0504c815f82b12534a9ae8558d8_100613_9427ca6963392d992712c474c93f5a8e.jpg&#34;
               width=&#34;200px&#34;
               height=&#34;322&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      This project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union&amp;rsquo;s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (Grant agreement No. 637915).
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Honesty</title>
      <link>https://www.behavioralethics.org/project/honesty/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behavioralethics.org/project/honesty/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3&gt;From cooperation to dishonesty: How concern for others can lead to unethical behavior&lt;/h3&gt;
Cooperation with others is common and beneficial in organizational as well as personal settings. Working together allows people to achieve mutually beneficial outcomes and prosper. While the benefits of cooperation are clear, recent work suggests that when people work together (rather than alone) they are more likely to engage in dishonest acts aimed at boosting their profit, apparently because it is easier to justify lying when others share the profit. It thus seems plausible that experiencing cooperation from counterparts may increase people’s likelihood to reciprocate, even when reciprocation requires bending ethical rules. The main aim of the proposed research is to explore whether, and how, cooperation increases people’s concerns regarding their counterparts’ outcomes, and thus encourages bending ethical rules in order to profit the cooperating others. Such dishonest reciprocation, may not only allow one to display care about the other’s outcome, but also increase the likelihood of future cooperation, potentially leading to a slippery-slope spiral of unethical misconduct. Addressing this possibility, a theoretical process-model is developed in which the degree of unethical behavior depends on the degree of experienced cooperation. Specifically, the proposed research has three aims: Identifying (1) situations in which experiencing cooperation translates into dishonest behavior benefiting the other; (2) psychological mechanisms underlying such dishonesty; and (3) situational factors that may remedy such undesired unethical behaviors. The model is systematically tested by employing experimental social psychological and behavioral economic paradigms. Beyond its theoretical contribution to understanding the effects of cooperation on unethical behavior, the project has societal relevance in crafting interventions tailored to boost ethical behavior in organizations and society.














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-this-project-has-received-funding-from-the-people-program-marie-curie-actions-of-the-european-unions-seventh-framework-program-fp72007-2013-rea-grant-agreement-number-333745&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;This project has received funding from the People Program (Marie Curie Actions) of the European Union’s Seventh Framework Program (FP7/2007-2013), REA grant agreement number 333745.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/FP7-logo_huec14192128ae1c245f67ae97ce0150ce_14452_4b796defbd7a86749ef34813be4c8f86.jpg 400w,
               /media/FP7-logo_huec14192128ae1c245f67ae97ce0150ce_14452_28352c08c0f9feed7ee385ac8c0c4e6f.jpg 760w,
               /media/FP7-logo_huec14192128ae1c245f67ae97ce0150ce_14452_1200x1200_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://www.behavioralethics.org/media/FP7-logo_huec14192128ae1c245f67ae97ce0150ce_14452_4b796defbd7a86749ef34813be4c8f86.jpg&#34;
               width=&#34;200px;&#34;
               height=&#34;360&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      This project has received funding from the People Program (Marie Curie Actions) of the European Union’s Seventh Framework Program (FP7/2007-2013), REA grant agreement number 333745.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Miscellaneous</title>
      <link>https://www.behavioralethics.org/project/miscellaneous/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.behavioralethics.org/project/miscellaneous/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3&gt; Miscellaneous: all our other stuff! &lt;/h3&gt; 
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
